Finding Aid for John R. Dethmers personal papers, 1942-2006
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
John R. Dethmers personal papers 1942-2006
Dethmers, John R., 1903-1971.
06130 Aa 2
Michigan Supreme Court Justice; personal papers including political materials, publications, and photographs.
2 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The John R. Dethmers personal papers were donated by Marjorie Dethmers Swyers (donor no. 9808 ) and came to the library in November 2006.
The collection is open to research.
John R. Dethmers was born October 15, 1903 in Plessis, Iowa. He graduated from Hope College in 1924 and the University of Michigan Law School in 1927. Admitted to the Michigan Bar that same year, he began practicing law in Holland, Michigan. In addition, he was prosecuting attorney for Ottawa County, 1931 to 1938, chief assistant attorney general of Michigan 1943 to 1944, then Attorney General of Michigan, 1945-1946. In 1946, he was appointed to the Michigan Supreme Court. In 1956, he was named the first permanent chief justice, serving 1956-1962; then again from 1967-1971. He was a member of the American Bar Association, the American Judicature Society, and the National Conference of Chief Justices. He died November 1, 1971.
The collection is arranged into a single series of Personal Papers. These include printed materials and files relating to his campaigns for office. The library also has a file of Judge Dethmers office files. The Personal Papers were retained by the Judge and his family for subsequent donation to the Bentley Historical Library. The interpretative comments accompanying some of the file headings were provided by Eugene G. Wanger who was helpful in negotiating this accession.
Subjects:
Dethmers, John R., 1903-1971.; Michigan. Supreme Court.
- Judge Dethmers Personal Papers
  - Michigan Supreme Court Historical Society website 2006; biographical page on Justice Dethmers (Box 1)
    (file #1)
  - "The Supreme Court on Freedom of the Press and Contempt by Publication," by Elisha Hanson, reprint from Cornell Law Review, February 1942 pp. 165-189 (Box 1)
    (file # 2)
  - Zoning Ordinance, City of Muskegon, Michigan 1952 (Box 1)
    (including city zoning map and an undated letter from architect objecting to the way certain residential property is zoned. Justice Dethmers joined a Muskegon law firm for a period upon his retirement.)
    (file # 3)
  - One Hundred Years of Law, An Account of the Law Office which John T. Stuart Founded in Springfield, Illinois, a Century Ago, by Paul M. Angle, Springfield, 1928, 55 pp. (Box 1)
    hardbound, with an August 1955 presentation letter to Justice Dethmers from Paul W. Gordon, the firm's senior partner. Stuart had been a partner of Abraham Lincoln.
    (file # 4)
  - Michigan State Bar Journal, January, 1953 (Box 1)
    (front cover a portrait of Chief Justice Dethmers, including a sketch of his life by Booth Newspapers Capital Correspondent Guy H. Jenkins at pp. 13-14)
    (file # 5)
  - "The Dubious Origin of the Fourteenth Amendment," by Walter J. Suthon, Jr., reprint from Tulane Law Review, December 1953 pp. 22-44, with addendum, inscribed by the author to Chief Justice Dethmers (Box 1)
    (file # 6)
  - American Bar Association Journal for January, 1959 (Box 1)
    (containing at pp. 47-49, 97 Dethmers' August, 1958 address in Los Angeles, as Chairman of the Conference of Chief Justices, to the Association's Section of Judicial Administration, containing his very respectful and deferential criticisms of the judicial activism of the United States Supreme Court, with portions of it underlined in red, most probably by his own hand. This address is believed by some to have cost Dethmers a presidential nomination to the Supreme Court of the United States.)
    (file # 7)
  - "High Court: A Shift to the Right," an article in Newsweek for June 22, 1959 pp. 21-22 (Box 1)
    (noting the several complaints of the Conference of Chief Justices (and others) against holdings of the United States Supreme Court since Earl Warren was appointed Chief Justice by President Eisenhower in 1953)
    (file # 8)
  - "Frontiers in Law and Legal Education, a program celebrating the centennial of the University of Michigan Law School October 22-24, 1958 (Box 1)
    (the 6-page program, listing Chief Justice Dethmers as one of the principal speakers; together with two copies of the 6-page program for the last day's centennial convocation awarding Chief Justice Dethmers an honorary Doctor of Laws degree.)
    (file # 9)
  - Texas Law Review for December, 1960 (Box 1)
    (including an article by Chief Justice Dethmers on Chief Justice John E. Hickman, of the Texas Supreme Court, and his work as chairman of the National Conference of Chief Justices, at pp. 133-135.)
    (file # 10)
  - Frontiers in Law and Legal Education, Addresses Given At the Centennial of the University of Michigan Law School, October 22, 23, 24, 1959 (Box 1)
    (published 1961, including Chief Justice Dethmers address at pp. 65-69 with a photograph of him receiving his honorary doctorate on p. 64)
    (file # 11)
  - The Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science for March 1960 entitled "Lagging Justice," (Box 1)
    (including an article by Chief Justice Dethmers titled "Delay in State Appellate Courts of Last Resort," at pp. 153-163)
    (file # 12)
  - Michigan in the War of 1812 Michigan Historical Commission, Lansing, 1960, 44 pp., paper covers (Box 1)
    (file # 13)
  - Michigan Alumnus for February 11, 1961 (Box 1)
    (including an article by F. Clever Bald on Michigan Men and the Civil War; with a copy of the issue for March 11, 1961; Michigan Alumnus Quarterly Review, for August 5, 1961 pp. 229-304. Dethmers had graduated from Michigan Law School in 1927)
    (file # 14)
  - Dedication of Additions to the American Bar Center, University of Chicago August 13, 1963 (Box 1)
    (20 pp.; together with illus. pamphlet on The American Bar Center, Chicago, 32 pp., in orig. envelope)
    (file # 15)
  - Monitor, Journal of the Professions, Michigan Association of the Professions, for February, 1964 with a picture of Chief Justice Dethmers on the cover. (Box 1)
    (file # 16)
  - Magna Carta, Text and Commentary, by A.E. Dick Howard, University of Virginia Press 1964 (Box 1)
    (55 pp., paper covers, w. presentation slip from the Magna Carta Commission of Virginia)
    (file # 17)
  - United States Supreme Court Opinion in Coleman v. Alabama June 22, 1970 (Box 1)
    (with a portion of Chief Justice Burger's dissent marked, almost certainly by Dethmers, emphasizing the danger of the Court acting as a "continuing Constitutional Convention.")
    (file # 18)
  - "A Tribute to Hiram C. Bond," from 382 Michigan Reports lxxiv-lxxxiii (November 6, 1969) (Box 1)
    (a unique ceremony honoring Mr. Bond on the occasion of his retirement after 43 years as the Michigan Supreme Court's Reporter, including some humorous banter between Justice Dethmers and Mr. Bond, specially bound in court-report buckram)
    (file # 19)
  - "The Paper Book of the Delta Theta Phi Law Fraternity" for May, 1970 (Box 1)
    (36 pp., including an article on the Christiancy Senate at the University of Michigan)
    (file # 20)
  - Virginia Law Review for December, 1970 (Box 1)
    (file # 21)
  - "Housing and Urban Development, A Selected, Annotated Bibliography," American Bar Association 1970 (Box 1)
    (23 pp., paper covers)
    (file # 22)
  - Journal of Law Reform, University of Michigan, Fall, 1970 160 pp (Box 1)
    (file # 23)
  - Michigan State Bar Journal for February, 1971 (Box 1)
    (including a photograph of Justice Dethmers, who retired at the close of 1970 after more than 24 years on the Court, nine as Chief Justice.)
    (file # 24)
  - Judicature, The Journal of the American Judicature Society for February, 1971 (Box 1)
    (file # 25)
  - Michigan Alumnus for April, 1971 (Box 1)
    (file # 26)
  - Michigan Alumnus for May, 1971 (Box 1)
    (file # 27)
  - "The Judge's Role in Dealing With Trial Disruptions," an American Bar Association pamphlet dated May, 1971 (Box 1)
    (file # 28)
  - Michigan State Supreme Court, Digest of 1969, 1970, 1971 cases, 17 pp. (Box 1)
    (file # 29)
  - State Bar of Michigan file
    (forwarded to the family in 1973)
    (file # 30)
    - Correspondence by the Bar recommending Dethmers for appointment to the Supreme Court of the United States 1957 (Box 1)
    - Resolutions unanimously adopted by the State Bar's Board of Commissioners to the effect that Dethmers should be appointed to the Supreme Courts. Resolutions were passed in 1954, 1956, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Studio photographic portrait of Justice Dethmers by Blackstone Studios, New York (Box 1)
    - Numerous newspaper clippings about Justice Dethmers from the Bar's clipping service, 1956-1970 pp. 5-7. (Box 1)
      (noting, inter alia, that he was the youngest justice ever appointed and the first Permanent Chief Justice and had wide support for appointment to the U. S. Supreme Court. Included is a photo-spread from the Detroit News Sunday Pictorial Magazine for March 30, 1958,)
  - "Personal-JRD" file folder including (Box 1)
    (inter alia, Finance Reports of Justice Dethmers' 1961 and 1970 campaigns for the Supreme Court, correspondence relating to appointment to the U.S. Supreme Court, a record of the Michigan Supreme Court Justices' voting for Chief Justice in 1963 and a 3-page handwritten list of Michigan Supreme Court citations titled, "Some of my opinions of special interest to me," in the Justice's own hand)
    (file # 31)
  - Miscellaneous, ca. 1957-1960 (Box 1)
    (including some humorous correspondence to Dethmers when Michigan Attorney General, a copy of his 1959 address at the Univ. of Michigan Law School centennial and his address of February 14, 1959 to the Massachusetts Bar Association entitled "On the Report of the Conference of Chief Justices," in which he answers the storm of criticism which that 1958 speech had produced. [Marked "(A)"]
    (file # 32)
  - Papers, correspondence and lists pertaining to Justice Dethmers' 1953, 1961 Supreme Court election campaigns. (Box 1)
    [Marked "(B)"]
    (file # 33)
  - Papers, correspondence and lists pertaining to Justice Dethmers' 1970 campaign (Box 1)
    (campaign in which he and Judge Piggins lost to former Democratic Governors Williams and Swainson; with an envelope of material on the 1966 Williams v. Griffin U. S. Senate campaign. [Marked "©)"])
    (file # 34)
  - "Invitations, Appearance Opportunities, etc. new--not yet scheduled" containing notes and papers pertaining to the 1970 campaign (Box 1)
    (file # 35)
  - "Campaign Appearances-Dethmers," containing lists, papers, memos and correspondence about Justice Dethmers' appearances around the state in the 1970 campaign (Box 1)
    (file # 36)
  - "Dethmers Campaign-Finance," containing miscellaneous solicitation letters and some "Re-elect Justice Dethmers, Supreme Court" bumper stickers 1970 (Box 1)
    (file # 37)
  - "Dethmers for Supreme Court Finances" 1971 (Box 1)
    (contains campaign contribution and expense reports with miscellaneous correspondence)
    (file # 38)
  - "Dethmers-Financial" (Box 1)
    containing mostly correspondence about contributions to Dethmers' 1970 campaign
    (file # 39)
  - Finance reports, lists, correspondence and bills paid in Justice Dethmers 1970 campaign. (Box 2)
    [Marked "(D)"]
    (file # 40)
  - Republican State Central Committee (Michigan), Press Kit 1970 (Box 2)
    (containing photos and campaign biographies of "all the state-wide Republican candidates" for 1970 including Justice Dethmers)
    (file # 41)
  - "Dethmers--Publicity," containing Justice Dethmers' 1970 campaign announcement, newspaper advertisement mat, text for radio spots, campaign vouchers, etc. 1970 (Box 2)
  - "Piggins, Edward," 1970 (Box 2)
    (containing mainly correspondence and clippings about Piggins' 1970 Michigan Supreme Court campaign, including letters from Piggins and his state chairman, Stephen S. Nisbet)
    (file # 43)
  - "Swainson, John B.," containing two of his 1970 Supreme Court campaign brochures (Box 2)
    (file # 44)
  - "Williams, G. Mennen," 1970 (Box 2)
    (containing correspondence and clippings and a Michigan Democratic Party campaign brochure regarding Williams' Supreme Court campaign)
    (file # 45)
  - "G.O.P. State Convention (August 28-29, 1970)" (Box 2)
    (containing the printed Convention Guide, the Platform Committee Report and a list of platform provisions of interest to Justice Dethmers' campaign)
    (file # 46)
  - "Dethmers For Supreme Court 1970" (Box 2)
    (containing a campaign manager's guide, Dethmers' August 1958 speech in Los Angeles that destroyed his chances for a U.S. Supreme Court appointment, campaign polling data from the Detroit papers, his campaign announcement, a detailed biography with handwritten corrections and post-election campaign correspondence, etc.)
    (file # 47)
  - "Return John R. Dethmers to the Michigan Supreme Court" postcards for the 1970 campaign (Box 2)
    (file # 48)
  - "Dethmers for Michigan Supreme Court" handout cards for the 1970 campaign (Box 2)
    (file #49)
  - Round 4-inch diameter bumper stickers printed "Re-Elect Dethmers, Supreme Court Justice" for the 1970 campaign (Box 2)
    (file # 50)
  - Envelope of 5 x 7 inch glossy black and white photos of Dethmers for the 1970 campaign (Box 2)
    (file # 51)
  - Block Plate-Picture of Supreme Court Justice John R. Dethmers as used on 1970 campaign posters by Murninghan Printing Co., in brown paper wraps (Box 2)
    (file # 52)
  - Video Tape Recording of Justice Dethmers' 10 second spot for his 1970 campaign, in WXYZ, Inc. mailing box (Box 2)
    (file # 53)
  - Inventory of personal property dated 06/21/1978 listing, inter alia, the many books in Justice Dethmers' large personal library (Box 2)
    (file # 54)
  - "Dad's Portrait file-To Supreme Court," 1979-1980 (Box 2)
    (containing correspondence and notes by Justice Dethmers' son Robert pertaining to the painting and presentation of the Justice's portrait to the Michigan Supreme Court, candidly disclosing some of the personal and political realities involved)
    (file # 55)
  - Thomas M. Cooley Law School, Commencement Exercises, the John R. Dethmers Class January 17, 1981 (Box 2)
    (including brief biography of Justice Dethmers together with newspaper clipping of the ceremony and a letter from the School to Aleen Dethmers, Justice Dethmers' widow, expressing Dean Thomas Brennan's "deep personal regard and admiration" for him, noting that this is the fifth anniversary of the opening of Cooley Law School)
    (file # 56)